So let's look at the right update
snooping coherence first. Let's look at
two caches only each of which has two
blocks with a single valid bit per block
and a tag and then the data and both of
these caches are connected to the same
bus to which we also connect the memory.
So now let's say that the caches are
initially empty. So the valid bits are
all zero. And this processor reads
something in block A. We have a cache
miss here. We send a request to memory.
This cache is always monitoring what's
going on on the bus, but it's only
interested in writes. So this read is
really going to be seen and ignored by
this cache. The data for A comes back
from memory. And now we put this block
in the cache. The block becomes valid.
And the tag, let's say, just indicates
that this is the block A. Now let's say
that this processor writes to A. So now
we have a situation where this processor
even if it does a right through access
directly to memory a read on this
processor would still read the stale
value of a. Let's say that the value we
read here was zero. Now let's say that
this processor writes one to a. this
right even if we made it go all the way
to memory would not result in coherent
behavior for this cache because a
subsequent read here would still hit in
the cache and get a zero. So this is
when write update and snooping come into
the picture. We have a cache miss but
because it's a write we send a request
for the block along with an indication
that it's a right and what is the value
and what's the address. So now what
happens is this request goes to memory
and the memory writes one to A. But more
importantly this cache is monitoring the
bus and sees that block A is being
updated. It checks its internal state
and sees that it has block A and then it
takes the value that is being written.
So this part is the snooping part where
we see what's going on on the bus. So we
cannot miss any of the rides happening
on another core because we're monitoring
the bus and all rightes have to go
through the bus. That's the snooping
part. The right update part is that when
we see a right, we update our copy of
the data with the value that is being
written. So this cache now gets a one
here. If we read a after this, we are
going to get this one. So this ensures
correct behavior. If there are multiple
cores, they cannot disagree about which
right happened first, which one happened
last because all of the rights are sent
through the bus and because it's a
single broadcast bus, it happens one at
a time. So all of them see rights in
exactly the same order in the order in
which writes got to the bus. Now let's
see what happens if both of these
processor try to write to a at about the
same time. So this is a situation where
they might disagree about whose right
happened first. Let's say that this one
is trying to write two and this one is
trying to write three. Well, there is a
single bus. So there is a single set of
wires that can carry the value and the
address and so on. So processors when
they want to send something on the bus
first have to arbitrate for it. And this
arbitration for the bus basically
decides who gets the bus next. If this
score won then it sends its right first.
Now both of the caches will have two.
This one because this is where the right
happened. This one because this is what
we pick up from snooping. And only then
after this is complete this right here
gets to occur. So now we go to three
broadcast that here and it gets here. So
as you can see both of them agree which
right was first and which was second.
Obviously the one that wrote three was
the second one because that's the last
value we kept. So the right update is
ensuring that rights are seen by reads
on all cores and the snooping of the
common bus and the serialization on that
bus basically going one at a time to the
bus is guaranteeing that everybody sees
the same order of rights.